PROFESSOR: All right. We are continuing with
the discussion of the broader patterns
of evolution. The next, this lecture and the
next lecture are covering similar grounds
in
a macroevolutionary context, that's what we're
building up to. And your final lab in this
section of the course is on macroevolution
using examples from horses. And I'll introduce
that today, these examples of horse evolution
to help introduce that lab.
This week is your final lab in phylogenetics,
right, with the primate phylogenetics?
You've already had some intro primates, so
some feedback there.
I'll talk about adaptive radiation which has
come up already, this whole idea of new
lineages forming in island contexts that so
stimulated Darwin and his contemporaries.
And
I'll look at some examples on how it sheds
light on evolutionary pattern and process,
evolutionary tempo and mode which are traditional
terms. A phrase, a book written by one
of the architects of the modern synthesis,
Tempo and Mode in Evolution by Simpson. Tempo
referring to the rate of evolution. Mode referring
to the shape of evolution. And we'll
try to unpack what all that means.
And then introduce punctuated equilibrium
which is something you may have heard of.
It's, at least it was part of popular culture.
You can still see cars in Berkeley with
bumper stickers that say "Honk if you look
punk eek" which is a reference to punctuated
equilibrium. Those were more popular. Those
bumper stickers may be in the 1980s, but
hey, it's still very much a current source
of study relating to the shape of evolution.
We'll talk about that and the tempo.
And then we'll look at another question that
we opened up earlier on, how complex
adaptations arise in evolution. For example,
the eye. We'll look at the eye example, the
one that Darwin was challenged on. How can
such a complex structure such as the eye
evolve?
And we'll look at mechanisms of evolution
involving exaptation and tinkering, this
concept of working with what's available rather
than inventing things from, inventing
things anew. Working with what's available
and then thus, innovating with the materials
at hand. That's part of those concepts.
All right. All of the these things today.
And then looking at islands now, let me see
if I can get, because this is a cool
recent video. I don't have the credit up here.
I'll get the credit onto your slides.
But a recent video showing the birth of islands
in ocean, literally, in, you know in
realtime, the way volcanos erupt under water
and that molten lava cooling with the, in
contact with the water can form new islands,
right? And this is the, how the Galapagos
were formed. It's how the Hawaiian Islands
are formed through this process. And you
know, these volcanos are essentially under
water mountains, volcanos, from the sea floor.
They can be extremely tall. If you drained
the ocean, you'd have an extremely tall
volcano, peaking its head up above the ocean
surface, right? So that's how literally
islands may evolve. And that's the story of
the Hawaiian Islands.
Your big island here, Hawaii, is the youngest
in this archipelago. The oldest
islands are to the Northwest. Right? And the
idea here, it relates to plate tectonics.
But in a some what unique way from the way
plate tectonics functions to create volcanos
at
the continental shelves, this is an archipelago
that's far from the continents. And the
hypothesis is that the Pacific plate in moving
in this direction is passing over a hotspot
deep under the lith, lithosphere. And so the
plate in moving over a deep hotspot
creates volcanic activity, and as a result
of plates' movements, the older islands get
carried toward the Northwest. And the younger
islands form down here in the southeast.
Thus, the ancient nature of these relative
to these.
And what's happened on the Hawaiian island,
they're relatively young. What's
happened is that you've had adaptive radiations
of the nature that Darwin was interested
in that I've described multiple times in the
patterning of island hopping of species.
And drosophila, the fruit flies famous for
the work on laboratory genetics on these
organisms, have speciated like crazy on the
Hawaiian Islands. So it's a spectacular
example of adaptive radiation. Specifically
these drosophila flies are radiating based
on
differences in where they lay their eggs.
Some are laying eggs on fungi. Some are laying
them on the leaves of plants. Some on the
stems of plants. They have differentiated
the
habitat in relation to their reproductive
activity. And created differences in that
regard that allow them to coexist.
And they've hopped from island to island and
changed along the way. Don't worry
about the numbers that are on this figure.
I just like the figure but the numbers are
inconsequential.
Another example from Hawaii, this modest little
plant, a tarweed from California or
from North America got to Hawaii and radiated
there. A little plant like this that has an
opportunity to travel that great distance
successfully may find itself on new islands
with
very few competitors, with very few established
large photosynthetic organisms with which
to compete. And is subjected to all the evolutionary
forces we've looked at. And has a
great opportunity in such a circumstance.
And that little creature having arrived has
radiated into all these forms, into these
mounding forms, into these leafy herbaceous
forms, into forms that look like, you know,
agave or maybe cactus-like forms, into small
trees or woody shrubs. All these variations
in morphology and ecology resulting from
ecological opportunities in this new landscape.
Here you have ages on the islands, showing
Hawaii with an estimated age of less than
half a million years. It's relatively young.
Would that have been, you know, and if you
think of these creatures having evolved in
this span of time, the oldest over 5 million
down to a million down to a half million,
well, is that timescale long enough in Darwinian
terms for evolutionary processes like this
to happen? Well, yeah. It must be because
that's how old the islands are and this is
the type of radiation you see.
These organisms don't exist anywhere else.
They don't exist on any other, on the
continents. There's no evidence that they
ever did. They're endemic to the Hawaiian
archipelago.
So certainly evolution can happen on that,
that span, scale of time. That span of
time.
Can it happen even faster? There's good evidence
from other settings that it can.
And I'm speaking of organisms like plants
and vertebrates here. But, let's not forget
about something like bacteria. We've been
hearing a lot in the news recently about super,
super bugs in hospitals, right? Antibiotic
resistant infections in hospitals. If you
haven't been reading the news, that it has
been widely in the news for years now. And
that's evolution that's occurring as these
organisms adapt to tolerate antibiotics in
hospital contexts or in medical contexts.
And that's evolution on a really rapid scale
in
bacteria, for example, which have very fast
generation times, very short generation times,
and rapid evolutionary potential.
Well, how about something like vertebrates
here? It's easier to understand the
rapidity in bacteria, but vertebrates, fish?
How quickly can fish evolve a bunch of
species? These African lakes function, they
function as islands. Thus, I had quotes in,
on islands in one of the earlier slides. Because
these lakes are essentially islands of
water in a sea of land if you will. Right?
They're isolated habitats in a different type
of habitat.
So lakes like these, Lake Malawi, Tanganyika,
in the East African rift, in the East
African Rift Valley, and lakes in the eastern
branch of the Rift Valley, and the giant
Lake Victoria that sits in between these rifts,
these lakes have been islands in which
evolution has occurred, specifically of cichlids
-- cichlid fish which have come up
previously -- to the tune of evolving four
to 500 species in these lakes which is a lot
of
species.
If you compare the Great Lakes of North America,
Lake Superior, that might have 20 to
30 species of fish in it. These lakes have
400, 500 cichlids alone. Forget all the
catfish and all the other fish. They're incredibly
speciose. Well, when did that happen?
These rift lakes are deep and ancient. Malawi
and Tanganyika are deep and ancient. They
hold a large quantity of the world's freshwater,
the whole planet's freshwater. So much
of the planet's freshwater is just in these
two lakes and Lake Biakal because of how deep
they are. And they're old.
So that could have happened on a great timescale.
But Lake Victoria, this is a
shallow lake that's formed by ponding up,
damming up rivers in the relatively recent
past.
Like maybe 40,000 years ago, 40- to 50,000
years ago. And then it seems to have dried
up
completely 14,000 years ago. So you'd have
almost as many cichlids in this lake as in
these. And that seems to have occurred in
that span of time. On a scale of 10, 20,000
years.
Or a little lake called Lake Nagu, Nagubob,
Nabugabo, I always pronounce wrong.
N-A-B-A-G-U-B-O. Not important, but that's
a picture of Nabugabo right
there. It's a fascinating little laboratory
of evolution. It's a little lake off of Lake
Victoria formed by a, dunes that formed and
separated it from Lake Victoria. This thing's
only a few thousand years old, Lake Nabugabo.
And in it you've had a radiation of
cichlids. So thousands of years for the evolution
of different vertebrate species.
These fishes are unique maybe in they're capacity
to evolve quickly. They have
adaptations in their jaws. They have unique
structure of their jaws that allows them to
differentiate their feeding niches in specialized
ways. I wouldn't go into the details,
but it involves of separation of pharyngeal
jaws into two parts that allows them to
capture food and chew food with separate mechanisms.
And they have complex modes of signaling in
sexual selection contexts. Unique
features that probably allow them to speciate
quickly relative to some other organisms.
So these aspects of their biology that create
a tempo of evolution that's rapid.
But a few thousand years is fast in Darwinian
terms. Darwin thought that things took
much longer or at least that's the typical
interpretation of Darwin's ideas.
A phyletic gradualism, right? Gradualism is
a phrase we've linked to him before.
Change by insensible degrees. So we can think
of Darwin as ascribing to a tempo of
evolution of that nature. And that would lead
to a particular shape of evolution. A slow
gradual changing in morphology. I'll have
a couple of diagrams in a minute that can
help
illustrate what shape that would imply.
But remember the problem for the fossil record
that that suggested because fossils
don't always show those clean links in form,
illustrating slow, gradual changes. So he
had a problem on his hands that he answered
by saying, well it's just a bad record. The
geological record is poor and doesn't capture
all those fine changes.
A big innovation occurred when, with a, with
the notion of punctuated equilibrium. A
theoretical innovation, a creative set of
ideas on the part of Stephen Gould and Niles
Eldredge. Names aren't important here, but
well-known investigators from the late 20th
century.
And Gould and Eldredge looked at the very
same evidence that everyone else had looked
at in terms of the fossil record and the distribution
of forms across strata over time.
And they took the record literally. And said,
well, what if this is a decent record?
What if it's not just a broken record here
and the data are sufficient for an analysis
of
how evolution unfolded? They reasoned that
in short periods of time, it's possible that
in short periods of time represented by a
single stratum, you might have had a lot of
change occur in form. And then over longer
periods of time, you would have periods of
stasis, S-T-A-S-I-S. Stasis, where relatively
little change occurred. So long
periods of equilibrium punctuated by rapid
periods of change.
And that's a really different interpretation
from the interpretation of phyletic
gradualism and signified a different shape
to the evolutionary process.
Stasis, long-term stasis is familiar in, for
organisms in the fossil record. Many
organisms represent long, long periods of
stasis and are sometimes called living fossils,
although it's a problematic descriptor. But
horseshoe crabs like these, you can see them
on beaches today, sometimes breeding in massive
numbers. Has anyone ever been on a beach
where the horseshoe crabs are breeding? Yeah.
A few of you? Was it on the East Coast,
the Atlantic Ocean? Do you remember where
it was?
STUDENT: North Carolina.
PROFESSOR: North Carolina.
STUDENT: Cancun.
PROFESSOR: Cancun. Yeah. It happens around
the world. It's typical of the eastern
U.S. and the Atlantic seaboard. These guys
are useful in medical research too. So
they're highly sought for their, their unique
type of blood. But still doing okay. But
readily harvested. And these things were basically,
look at this guy from the Jurassic,
175 million years ago. Well it's a horseshoe
crab. You can see it from a distance. It's
still a horseshoe crab. Barely changed its
overall form. Now it could be a carnival at
the molecular level in terms of changes. We
can't see what's happening at the molecular
level from a fossil like this in comparison
to an organism like this. So there could be
a
lot of change happening at other levels. But
in gross morphology, long-term stasis here.
This is longer term stasis than was even considered
by the, by Gould and Eldredge. But
examples of extreme forms of stasis.
Or the Dawn redwood trees, which you were
probably introduced to in the last section,
right? Metasequoia, a relative of redwoods
and sequoias, that was only recently
discovered. It's a great story. Recent discovery
in China in the 1940s. A grove of
these trees was found. Soon after it had been
described from the fossil record from the
Mesozoic, from dinosaur times, terrestrial
dinosaur times, the fossils of these had been
found and described and then a few years later,
a living stand of them was found growing
in these ravines, these remote ravines in
China. And then World War II happened and
there
was a delay. And after global situation calmed
down, an expedition was run from, from
Harvard of scientists to go collect seeds
of it. And so you have, you have these trees
on
the Berkeley campus. Several of them, right
around the building in the vicinity of
building. And some of them date to that time
because these seeds were taken and the
Harvard biologists sent them to different
universities and arboreta to plant. And it
was
a remarkable case of an ancient form for which
the record was lost for many millions of
years that was found to still exist today.
It's a living fossil that hasn't changed its
form to too great an extent over time over
time. Vast period of equilibrium.
Darwin seemed to imply that organisms would
constantly change. If this is morphology
on this axis, and this is time on this axis,
then your morphological features are going
to
gradually drift over time and slowly. And
sometimes the drifting will involve a branching
as to lineages split and become different
things, sufficiently different that they don't
maintain their integrity as one line but become
two lines. This is called anagenetic
change. Just write it on the board instead
of fighting with my, my tablet to do it.
Anagenesis. Anagenesis refers to that type
of change in lineages that occurs through
the
gradual changes through time and can lead
to must forms. As opposed to cladogenesis
where
the changes are concentrated at the branching,
at the branching events them.
So here with the same axes, let's take a look
at this with the same axes, right? If
this is morphological change, that's a great
amount of morphological change occurring in
no time at all, because time is on your y-axis,
right? So here's a lineage that's living
through time in stasis. This would represent
stasis. No morphological change. Rapid
amount of morphological change in virtually
no time at all. At least with reference to
the geological record and its ability to capture
these phenomena. And then ongoing
stasis. So equilibrium punctuated by a lot
of change and more equilibrium.
The shape of this is different from the shape
of this. This is rectangular in form.
The branching pattern, it's squared. It's
you know 90-degree angles. Sometimes called
rectangular. And it's cladogenesis, where
the clades arise rapidly in time. And the
changes concentrate, concentrated at the lineage
branching event. Here the change occurs
all along as well as at the branching event.
Here it's concentrated at the splitting
events them.
And that's really a gradualism contrasted
with punctuated equilibrium. Let's put
some organisms on it for reference. Butterflies
that have different color patterns.
Right? So different gross morphology, different
form of these butterflies. Here's, from
starting from this relatively muted brown
butterfly in the gradualism model, they would
gradually change, form over time, becoming
more orange here. Maybe with some white bands
here until they ended up as different forms.
Here's your original dull model in a
punctuated equilibrium context that branches
to form an orange type and some other type
relatively quickly. Different shapes to the
process, leading to an end result that may
be
similar, an orange one and a white one and
maybe your original type as well. "Punk eek."
The real geeks will say "punk eek", that's
shorthand for punctuated equilibrium. Yes,
please.
STUDENT: So what's a bigger factor of rapid
gene flow or just rapid [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: So what's a bigger factor in the
punctuated equilibrium model? Is it a
lack of gene flow or some other mechanism?
Yeah, it's a great question because what
you're getting at is the question I think
as to whether the mechanisms are different
in
punctuated equilibrium vs. gradualism. And
that really was the heart of the debate
because when this model was advanced by Gould
and Eldredge, it was taken to be
anti-Darwinian. Some non-Darwinian mechanisms
must be responsible for this model to work.
And mostly they said no, we're just talking
about traditional Darwinian mechanisms on
different timescales and concentrated in different
portions of the evolution of these
lineages. So they didn't introduce any new
mechanisms of change.
There are results from recent times, particularly
in the field of evolutionary
developmental biology, evo-devo, evolutionary
developmental biology that I'll look at in
the next lecture that can help explain periods
of very rapid change that are in some ways
non-Darwinian maybe. And also types of genetic
change that, that can lead in single
generations to lineage splitting that we've
already looked at with cases of polyploidy.
Phenomena like that are relevant here maybe,
for some lineages at least. But mostly, the
punctuated equilibrium folks were saying,
no, we're talking about traditional mechanisms.
This was a study right in the heart of that
debate that seemed to support a
punctuated equilibrium model. Again these
Great Lakes of Africa. In this case molluscs
and the shape of the evolution of the mollusc
tree in these African lakes. Looking at
fossils, an excellent fossil record going
way back in time. These organisms seemed to
have periods of stasis punctuated by rapid
change, continued by periods of stasis. There
was just an example of support for punctuated
equilibrium that was published in a, you
know, in the major journal of the world nature
and received a lot of press. It's also
received significant challenges since then.
But there was and is evidence to support a
punctuated equilibrium model.
Just a reminder about the doors. I've had
multiple requests to try not to slam doors
on your way out and in. Those things slam
and can be disruptive.
Horses are really interesting case study in
this context. And they'll be the focus
of your lab next week. This is a, horses have
been studied in evolutionary contexts for
a
long, long time. Textbook sort of example.
There's a lecture this morning, 10:00 a.m.
on
this campus, in this building on the evolution
of horses. So if you want the details on
that, it starts at 10:00. And it's taking
a genomic approach to modern horses. But the
data shed light on these ancient patterns
in interesting ways.
So the horses are just fas -- horses are fascinating
to people, the beloved noble
horse. Right? Where would we be today without
horses? Well they did play a huge role in
our history. They evolved from modest little
creatures, you know the size of a, the size
of a dog, these ancient horses from 60 million
years ago, Eohippus. The Dawn horse.
Hippus refers to horse. Hippopotamus is the
river horse. Eohippus, Eo, ancient Dawn,
from the earliest days, the ancient horse.
Well these guys were, yeah, they were tiny,
like this. And they had lots of toes. Well
not lots. I mean five or fewer is typical
for vertebrates. And these guys had four good
toes on their feet. And over time you have
this trend over increasing size and loss of
toes to the modern condition where your noble
horses just running on its middle fingers
and middle toes. It's running on one finger.
Indeed it's running on the distal bone and
hoof of the one finger. The others having
been
reduced and lost completely or just present
as these little splints, which if you're an
equestrian you know about horses that they
have these two bones on either side which
represent the vestiges of the ancient bones
of digit two and digit four that, that have
essentially gone away.
Not only has height changed and the number
of toes changed, but the tooth form has
changed from the ancient types that had relatively
low crowned teeth, the portion of the
tooth that's above the gum line is the crown,
and the roots below that, well, this is a
low crowned tooth because there's a relatively
small amount of crown relative to the
roots. It's about equal. That's low crowned.
As opposed to a high crowned tooth like
your modern horse has in the barnyard, it
has a very high crown and only a little bit
of
root. This is all the root right there. All
the rest is crown.
And these three phenomena, height, size, number
of toes, and heights of teeth have
been part of an integrated story of horse
evolution. Does anyone know the general
contours of that story? What do all these
three things relate to in horses? Or maybe
you
can just present a hypothesis. Maybe you've
never heard but ... can you generate any
creative idea there? A roomful of geniuses.
I know there's stirring minds out there but,
yes.
STUDENT: [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: Teeth had to do with a change in
diet. Yes, they did. And an emphasis
on foods that are harder to chew. Specifically
grasses. Grass is really hard to chew if
you've ever tried compared to leaves or fruit,
which these little guys probably were
emphasizing in more forested contexts, leaves
and fruits, grasses are full of silica.
They're impregnated with silica. The stuff
that sand or glass is made from, right, and
that wears away the teeth. So you better have
a high crown of, on your teeth if you're
going to wear it that much or you'll wear
them out and you won't be able to chew any
more.
And that can happen to horses.
So high crowned teeth correlated with eating
grass in open spaces where running is at
a premium. Being tall with long legs allows
you to be faster. And losing toes helps you
to reduce the weight in the distal extremities
and allows you to have a longer stride and
a faster stride in open country grasslands
as you evolve away from forests. It's a lovely
study. And it fits this type of linear trajectory.
But when you look at horse evolution
you see how, just how many lineages there
are. All these different lineages named based
on differences in morphology. Not molecular
biology. Yet. But, it's stirring.
So what you've done when you make a story
like that is essentially follow one track
through this complex web of history. And tell
a story on that basis of that one track.
You go from your Dawn horse following one
track line to the modern horse. And create
one
linear narrative about all these, all this
complex evolution. And all these failed
pathways, if you want to consider them that.
Yes?
STUDENT: Where do zebras come in.
PROFESSOR: Zebras are way up here. Zebras
are members of the genus Equus. This,
very closely related to your domestic, domestic
horse. You have the thing called Equus
Przewalski in Mongolia that's thought to be
the direct ancestor of the modern horse.
Zebras are closely related. There's a zebra-like
creature that recently went extinct
called the quagga. And I know the guy today
talking has genetic data from the quagga.
So
they're just, they're just a horse. Yeah.
STUDENT: [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: Same species as your domestic horse.
The ponies. Yeah, all considered
Equus caballus. Same species as the domestic
horse.
So, and these lines that even a diagram like
this connecting all the dots, these are
hypotheses about the evolutionary connections.
In reality, just have fossils from a
certain time period. You have fossils of,
is that Parahippus here, Pliohippus,
Merychippus. We have fossils that represent
these different types. You may know that
they run from 25 to 15 million. But to connect
these up into a story involves further
suppositions.
So we can't naively tell these stories of
linear trajectories. We have to recognize
that they're hypotheses built on hypotheses.
And the traditional story of horse evolution
is one of gradual change relating to a modern
condition that's the apex of the whole
process. The noble horse of today.
And it all culminated in that. Well, it was
a branchy messy process with lots of ins
and outs. And we shouldn't be selective in
our storytelling. We also don't need to
necessarily choose between punctuated evolutionary
patterns and gradualistic patterns as
being one or the other. Different organisms
might evolve in different ways, according
to
their mode and tempo. And even the same organisms,
one lineage might at different times
exhibit the different patterns. So as usual
we can't naively just accept one perspective.
We need to hold multiple perspectives in mind.
We need to be multifactorial, which will
be really true in ecology, in the ecology
section. Ecologists love multiple causality.
So true novelties in evolution, true creativity,
that's a lasting problem. How do
you get something from nothing? That goes
back to that old philosophical problem. What
I'm going to address as one answer is this
phenomenon of tinkering.
And the gradual building up of complex neomorphs.
Remember the eye was the problem.
An organ of extreme perfection like the eye,
how could it, what good is half of an eye?
It couldn't be built by natural selection
step-by-step because half of an eye is no
good.
You need the whole thing or nothing.
Mollusks show a great example in the world
of living mollusks, the different stages
of complexity in eyes that could represent
the stepping-stones along which eyes evolved.
Limpets, these little creatures like limpets
or chitons that cling to the rocks down
on the, on the ocean shore, they have a type
of eye that just essentially is a series of
pigmented cells. So they can perceive light
and dark only. Which is useful. Better than
no eye because if a shadow crosses over them
that may be a predator, may be something that
threatens them at least they know that there's
something overhead and maybe they should
cling tighter rather than trying to be active
in moving at that time. So simple pigmented
cells representing an eye are useful and functional.
They don't do what the hawk's eye
does. But at least it's positive benefit to
the organism and can be explained as evolving
by natural selection.
Organisms like nautiloids. This is a living
creature called a nautiloid, still
exists. Well, it has a somewhat more complex
eye that's, functions like a pinhole camera,
that has an aperture that can be opened and
closed to allow more or less light in and
to
give the organism some sense of depth-of-field.
If you know something about the way an
aperture functions on a camera. There's even
a step in between that we could have drawn,
just forming a cup, an eye cup. On your PDF
I, I have a link which you can look, you can
go to for a very entertaining description
of eye evolution to enliven this that's given
by
Richard Dawkins who's a popular biologist
in an easy to listen to presentation on this
subject.
Conchs, I mean look at those funny eyes. Starting
to resemble more of what we think
of as an eye maybe on these long stalks. Well
they have a lens that not only allows some
depth perception but allows a better focus
of the image. So not only can they see depth,
but some clarity of what's moving in front
of them. All steps that are very useful in
vision. When you get to the cephalopods, like
quid and octopus and cuttlefish, you have
a
very complex eye with all the features really
that we have in our eyes, including the
cornea and the lens and the retina. A complex
camera eye like this. But it's differently
corrected from ours. It's convergent. It's
convergently evolved on the vertebrate eye.
Some day you must save up your money to go
to a place where you can snorkel with
squid because you'll, it's an unforgettable
thing when you end up with a school of squid,
cephalopods, and they all turn and look at
you at once with these eyes, it's unbelievable.
I mean it's like you're looking at a bunch
of mammals in a watery context and they're
all
synchronized and changing their colors in
synchrony. Organisms are not thought to be
able
to see color. Traditionally that's the notion.
You have a GSI in this course who's
studying that right now. He's got some cuttlefish
up in his lab. And he's, he seems to
be challenging that notion that these cephalopods
with their complex eyes can't see color.
Fascinating little study happening in the
building upstairs.
The hawk's eye, the vertebrate's eye is differently
constructed as I mentioned. It's
actually an inferior construction in many
ways because of the way that the, and I don't
know enough about this, but the way that the
photo pigment receptors are constructed,
they're reversed from the cephalopod's eye.
And it creates a blind spot in vertebrates
because of the bundling of the nerves at the
back of the eye. A blind spot for the
vertebrates that the cephalopods don't have.
So in many ways the cephalopod eye is a
superior construction.
But why isn't the vertebrate eye better? It's
not the way evolution proceeds by
doing the optimum. It works with what's available.
Evolutionary processes can get caught
in cul-de-sacs that are irreversible. And
it's one of the great examples for a natural
process here because if you wanted to do this
process ideally, you would construct
organisms perfectly and differently. And the
vertebrate eye is an imperfect construction.
It's certainly the cephalopod eye can be improved
upon.
I don't have time for this video but I'll
send you a link. It's an introduction to
this phenomenon of exaptation. And it describes
pitcher plants well. Pitcher plants are
one of these carnivorous plants, right, that
consume insects by, in the case of the
pitcher plants, having a watery medium inside
them that the insects fall into. And end up
being digested by the plant. A great adaptation
on the part of plants particularly that
are living in nitrogen and phosphorus poor
environments.
They can't get their, these essential elements
from the soil. So they get them from
these animals that fall in and then fall into
this acidic bath and get digested. The
video is even more spectacular because it
shows just what a complex system this is.
It's
not just the plants that are eating the insects
but there's a little spider that lives in
there that steals the food. But in defecating
and digesting these insects also feeds the
plant. And then a crab that wants to eat the
spiders and as usual it's a complex story.
But the point here is about exaptation. And
the fact that, well what is a pitcher?
You guys know your plants, up down, left and
right now. What is, what is this? This --
modified leaf, yes. These are modified leaves.
So this organism in needing a capture
device hasn't invented a whole new organ for
capturing insects. It's modified leaves.
It's tinkered with stuff it already had. Tinker
Bell, I've learned from my daughter, was,
I mean that's in the root, that's in the root
of her name. Tinker Bell is a, was a child
who used to work with metal pots and pans
or something like this, and create like, teapots
from them or something. I don't know. But,
would tinker, would use the object at hand
to
create new objects. She was Tinker Bell, she
was a tinkerer. It's kind of an old
fashioned word that people, saying, oh, you're
just tinkering over there, aren't you Sonny
or something like that, right? No one says
that anymore. But, to tinker, that's the
idea.
And the French made it famous because they
had a term that translates as tinker,
called bricoler, B-R-I-C-O-L-E-R. So that's
where it became current in English, from
the French translation. Because these French
guys were strong on pointing out that so
much of evolution happens through tinkering,
working with what you have. A structure
that's evolved for one function originally
is exapted, it's co-opted, it's co-opted for
a
new function. A structure that's evolved for
one function and becomes co-opted for a new
function is called an exaptation.
And so much of evolution has happened through
that process. The Venus Flytrap and
its capture device is also based on modified
leaves for the same purposes, capturing
insects in nutrient-poor environments.
Or as a final example, the topic that's comes
up already, it's so fascinating in a
modern context, the relationship of birds.
And specifically now this great synapomorphy
of the avian lineage that is feathers. Feathers,
you can't find feathers on anything else
other than birds and their close relatives.
So what are feathers? Feathers are uniquely
constructed for what? For flying with, right?
Well there are a couple of different types
of feather. And the dinosaurs, the early dinosaurs,
and there are several now, there are
several nice ones, mostly from China. One
hundred twenty million years from microraptor,
125 or so for Sinornithosaurus. Sinosauropteryx,
125, around the same time here. Well
preserved in these slabs of material, showing
evidence for feathers on the bodies of these
creatures.
These tend to be the little downy-type feathers,
the down feathers, the fluffy little
ones that young birds have, the type that
are good for your sleeping bag or your
comforter, because they're particularly insulating
and warm.
Maybe that's why feathers evolved in these
little creatures, to keep them warm?
Okay. It's a good possibility given the fact
that you're not seeing the long asymmetrical
feathers typically used in flight on these
ancient forms. So see how you have a scenario
here whereby you could have downy feathers
evolving in the precursors. And those feathers
being exapted for flight in creatures like
Archaeopteryx, the famous transitional organism
between dinosaurian reptiles and modern birds.
And there are intervening possibilities with
feathers between insulation and flight
too. Because feathers are rich in signaling
possibilities. So they could also be
co-opted for patterns in sexual selection.
And even flight after that. A few different
scenarios possible to test with the fossil
record and molecular studies potentially.
All right. All set for today. Have a nice
week.