PROFESSOR: Good morning. Today's lecture begins
what is probably conceptually the
most difficult topic that we're going to be
presenting in this portion of the class on
plants. Is this loud enough? It is on. Can
you make the microphone louder? I'm sorry
my voice is a bit ... how about now? Better?
Good. All right.
So with today's lecture what we do is we begin
a discussion of what is conceptually
probably the most difficult topic presented
in the class portion on plants.
Today we're going to talk about water relations
in plants. And in order to help you
understand this topic and to appreciate it,
and in order to make sure that you understand
it for the class, we have several aids. The
first is that next week your lab is going
to
stress water relations. You're going to be
doing some of the experiments that we talk
about today. And that hopefully will help
you solidify some of these rather abstract
concepts.
Also we're giving you a problem set for the
fourth lab. This problem set is exactly
the same problem set as we've given out in
previous years. It is, you could easily just
copy the answers from somebody who took the
class last year. But my hope is and
suggestion is that you don't do that. Use
the problem set as a way of telling yourself
whether or not you really understand water
relations. This is the time to solidify those
concepts in your mind because you won't have
an opportunity later on once you get into
ecology and evolution to make sure that you
understand the material.
So make sure that you take advantage of the
problem set. They are not hard. They're
to help you to convince you that you do or
do not understand water relations.
Now of the processes that are unique to plants,
probably the most unique one, of
course, is photosynthesis. But running a close
second as far as the processes that go on
in plants and that are unique to them is the
transport of water over very great distances
of the plant. For example, to the top of a
redwood tree, without the aid of any kind
of a
pump, any kind of mechanical system. And today
what we want to do is to talk about this
very unique process, to talk about the mechanism
by which water is moved great distances
in plants without the aid of any kind of mechanical
instrumentation.
And at the outset I want to mention to you
that when we talk about water relations
and water movement which is what we'll be
talking about today, the concepts and the
equations which apply to this particular physiological
reaction apply to water movement in
all living systems, in your bodies, in insects,
in fish. So although you may say that
this is vague and it's not something you're
going to see again, if any of you go on to
animal physiology or into medicine, you want
to understand how the kidney works, it
follows exactly the same sorts of principles
that we're going to discuss today.
In order for us to appreciate water movement
in the plant, we have to divide the
topic into two sub-portions. And the first
portion is the properties of the water
molecule. And the second property or discussion
point that we want to talk about is the
nature of the plumbing system.
And I'd like to begin by discussing properties
of the water molecule that are
important. And for this demonstration, for
this first topic I want to do a slight
demonstration here for you. And I'm just going
to pour some pure water into this
crystalizing dish. And then I'm going to take
this razor blade, which is denser than the
water, and put it on the surface of the water.
And for those of you sitting up here in
front, you'll notice that the razor blade
floats. Even though it's heavier on a per
unit
area or per square weight area than the water,
it stays on the surface of the water.
And this property that the water has which
allows the razor blade to float is an
important property in understanding water
movement in plants.
This property is called surface tension. And
on a molecular level if we look at the
water molecule, the basis of surface tension
rests on the fact that in the water molecule
the electrons tend to spend more time around
the oxygen than they do around the hydrogens.
And so there's an overall more negative charge
around the oxygens. And a more positive
charge around the hydrogens. And this results
then in the development of a bond that most
of you have already had introduced to you
either in high school chemistry or introductory
chemistry here known as a hydrogen bond.
This allows for the surface of the water to
support the blade, the surface tension.
We sometimes say that the water is sticky,
that is the water molecules stick to each
other, or a more technical term which you
will see used in the textbook is that it
illustrates cohesion. Cohesion is a property
of the water molecule.
So the first property that we want to keep
in mind is that water molecules exhibit
cohesion. And they can form hydrogen bonds
between individual molecules.
The second property which we want to talk
about with regard to water molecules is
that water evaporates, that is it goes from
a liquid to a gas phase. And the speed with
which water evaporates, the rapidity, depends
on the temperature and on the humidity.
And knowing the temperature and humidity in
any particular environment, one can
calculate a number for how rapidly water will
evaporate. And that number gives us a value
which is known as the vapor pressure gradient.
A value for helping us to understand how
rapidly evaporation will occur, how quickly
water will go from a liquid to a gas state.
Now having discussed these two molecular properties
of the water molecule, I want to
now discuss with you three principles which
govern water movement. And we'll write them
out, and then we'll discuss each of them individually.
The first principle is known as mass flow.
The second principle which we need to
understand in order to appreciate how water
gets up to the top of tall trees is diffusion.
And the third principle, probably the most
familiar to you of the three, is osmosis.
Let's begin with mass flow by defining it.
And what we will say is mass flow is
movement of water from a region of higher
concentration
to a region of lower
concentration.
Now what do I mean by higher concentration
and lower concentration of water? Here I
have two beakers. And I'm going to just take
this pure water and pour some into each of
these two beakers. So there's nothing else
in this beaker except water molecules.
And now into one of these beakers, let's say
the one here on the left, I'm going to
add some table sugar or salt to the beaker.
And we're going to dissolve this table salt
or the sugar in the beaker. And now if I could
magically dissolve the two walls
separating these two liquid solutions -- that
is the pure water and the water which now
contains the sugar -- so that the water on
the two beakers can now flow together, what
we
would find is that water would flow from where
it is more pure to where it is less pure.
It is going from where it is more concentrated
to where it is less concentrated. So
in this particular beaker, we have more than
just water dissolved in the beaker. We have
salts or sugars, whatever it is we put into
the beaker. So water moves from where it is
more concentrated to a region where it's less
concentrated or from where it is pure to a
region where it is less pure. Very important
point for you to understand.
Now the potential of water to move
can be measured. And when we make this
measurement -- and we're going to be doing
that in the lab and we'll talk about it some
more -- we call this potential, we call it
the water potential. Potential to move, it's
called the water potential.
And it is indicated by the Greek letter psi.
This is the way you will have it in
your lab notes and in the lab next week.
Now, I want to take you to another system
because I want you to understand how we put
numbers on the water potential. When we measure
temperature, arbitrarily we set the
freezing point of water as zero degrees centigrade.
Everything else is compared to zero
degrees centigrade. So we have a reference
point in the temperature to which we compare
everything else.
We have the same type of reference point for
water relations. And that reference
point is pure water. So we arbitrarily say
that the water potential of pure water, that
is nothing else is dissolved in this beaker,
the only molecules present in this beaker
are
water molecules, we arbitrarily set the water
potential of pure water as equal to zero.
So the psi of pure water equals zero. Important
point. And what this means, which
is the confusing part, it means anything dissolved
in water lowers the water potential.
And this translates into a negative number.
Now we can measure water potential. And as
I said we're going to be doing it in the
lab in the class. And there are various units
which are attached to it, depending upon
whether you're a biologist or a chemist or
a physicist. Some of the units you will see
attached are bars, atmospheres. Again, it
depends upon which discipline you're in
depending upon which units we actually attach
to the water potential number.
Aside from being able to measure the water
potential, we can also measure how much of
the contaminating species is dissolved in
the water. And this species, in this particular
case salt, can be more than just sodium chloride.
It can be many salts. And so we give a
name to all the species which are dissolved
in the water and we call them solutes.
Solutes represent the total of all the species
that are dissolved in the water.
And we can measure the total number of species
dissolved. And we indicate that total
number dissolved by again the Greek letter
psi. And depending upon again which book
you're using or which notation, it's equally,
it's sometimes indicated psi sub-pi or your
textbook indicates it as psi sub- s for solutes.
And this represents then the total
value of solutes. And again it has the same
units that we talked about before.
So these represent then important aspects
of the dissolving of solutes in the water.
Now having introduced you to these particular
concepts here, what I want to do now is
to return to the second of the two principles
we talked about, namely, to talk about
diffusion.
And we can define diffusion as the overall
movement of water or, it doesn't have to
be water, just overall movement of a species,
it could be more, from a region of high
concentration to lower concentration until
the distribution is equal throughout
the
system.
And when we get this equal distribution throughout
the system of whatever the ion is
or species we're looking at or solid is, we
say we reach equilibrium. And for this
discussion we can say that when the diffusing
ion or diffusing species let's say is water,
then mass flow and diffusion are the same.
And to illustrate this point I have here some
blue dye which is very concentrated in
this dropper bottle. And if I introduce this
dye into this particular beaker at one
portion of the beaker, the dye is going to
now diffuse from where it is most
concentrated -- namely, the drop -- over time
so that its concentration is equal
throughout the entire beaker. And at that
point we will say that the species, in this
case the blue dye, is in equilibrium with
the solution that it's dissolved in. An
pointer.
Finally I want to mention to you the third,
third aspect of the principles which
govern water movement. And that third aspect
is osmosis. And this is something which
you're going to explore in the lab and perhaps
some of you have already done so in your
high school biology classes.
So we're going to talk about osmosis. And
what we can define osmosis as it is the
diffusion of water through -- and for water
we could also put other solutes if you want
to
use them, but normally it's water -- diffusion
of water through a selectively permeable
membrane.
And this can be shown, and you're going to
do this in the class, by the construction
of a device known as an osmometer. And let's
just look at the main elements of the
osmometer, which again you're going to make
in class.
So for this particular example of the osmometer
we'll have a beaker which contains
pure water. So because the water is pure,
the psi equals zero. And into this beaker
we're going to introduce a tube like so. And
this tube then is going to have at one end
a
selectively permeable membrane. It's going
to be attached securely, as you will do in
the
lab, selectively permeable membrane to one
end of the tube.
Then into this tube you're going to introduce
water plus some solute. So that means
that the water potential of the solution you're
introducing, the water potential is some
negative number. Everybody clear on that?
So again, following the basic principles of
water moving from where it is in higher
concentration to where it is in lower concentration,
and given that the selectively
permeable membrane if this particular experiment
only allows water to move through it, not
our solute, we would expect that water would
go from where it is more concentrated to
where it is less concentrated. That is it
would move into the tube, and you can measure
the force moving into the tube by the rise
in the water column in the osmometer.
So this is an experiment which you will conduct
in the lab. And again it is meant to
illustrate for you one of the main principles
that we have to consider with regard to
water relations, water movement in all living
organisms.
Now what I'd like to do is to switch the topic
slightly and to talk about the other
aspect of the water movement and that is to
talk about the plumbing system; that is the
pathway that water follows. So we're going
to talk about the plumbing system.
And we're going to draw a couple of these
elements on the plumbing system for us to
use. And in this particular case we're going
to start out with the stem which you,
nothing that's going to be any new to you.
We have the root system. And we have the
leaf. And then we want to add a few more elements
onto this particular drawing so we can
begin to appreciate the water movement.
One element that we want to add are the stomata.
And recall we said the stomata
CO2 enters and water leaves. Or water evaporates.
The only other element we need to add to this
drawing is the cell type, which in the
stem transports the water, and that's the
xylem which we said, depending upon whether
it
was a gymnosperm or an angiosperm, consists
of tracheids and vessels or vessel elements.
Now, in order for us to look at this cartoon
and to put it together with the
principles of water movement, I want to give
you a statement which we're going to explore
in more detail but one which forms the basis
of understanding water movement in the plant.
And that statement is that the driving force
for water movement in plants is the
evaporation of water from the surface of the
leaf.
Now I'd like to explore this statement a little
more with the principles that we have
and with this cartoon that we have drawn over
here. And for this discussion what I'd like
to do is to put some real numbers for water
potential on the various aspects of the
plumbing system.
The first is to give you a real number for
the water potential of the atmosphere.
That is, how much water is dissolved in the
atmosphere. There are lots of other things
in
the atmosphere. So realistic number around
here for the water potential for the
atmosphere would be maybe -20. Now how about,
what would be a realistic number for the
water potential of the leaf? The leaf is a
living system. It has membranes. It has
salts which are part of the living system.
So a reasonable value for the water potential
inside the leaf might be a psi equal of -8.
And then we'll talk about these other two
aspects of the water system in a moment.
Now let's look at just following the water
potential equations that we talked about
before, what's going to happen to a water
molecule? As a water molecule comes to the
surface of the leaf and is exposed to the
atmosphere, it is at a water potential of
-8
compared to the water potential of the atmosphere
of -20 where there's less concentration
of water.
Yes?
STUDENT: [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: Pardon me? Units are whatever ones
you want to use. Again, depending
upon whether you're a physicist, a mathematician
or whatever. Doesn't make any
difference. It's the same principles.
STUDENT: [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: -8 bars, -8 atmospheres, -8 Pascal's,
again it just depends upon what
you're coming from as far as discipline.
So here we have a -8 inside the leaf compared
to a -20 in the atmosphere. And so now
the water is going to want to go from where
it is more concentrated or pure to where it
is
less concentrated. And at this point the water
leaves the leaf. And when it leaves the
leaf, it evaporates. It breaks the hydrogen
bonds.
So, the evaporation of water from the leaf
is the starting point for the mechanism.
And we call this evaporation of water from
the leaf transpiration. Transpiration. Now
let's see what happens as this water is beginning
to evaporate from the leaf, it is still
attached to other water molecules in this
particular stem. And they now are beginning
to
come under tension. The bonds between, the
hydrogen bonds between the adjacent water
molecules are beginning to stretch. And you
can kind of indicate it with this rubber band
with these yellow things meant to indicate
the water molecules.
Here we are in the xylem of the tree and now
transpiration is occurring. And as
transpiration occurs, a tension is applied
to the bonds and they begin to stretch. They
begin to stretch like so. And this stretching
essentially pulls the water molecules up
the tree. So the driving force for the movement
of water up to the tree is the fact that
evaporation is causing a buildup of tension.
And this tension is lifting the whole column
of water in the tree.
Until it reaches the point where the tension
is so great at this region over here
that the hydrogen bonds break and the water
molecule evaporates. So very important point.
Now we can measure this tension which develops
inside the tree as a result of the
water evaporating. And it is indicated, a
measure of the tension is indicated by the
Greek letter psi sub-p. Measure of tension
that develops inside. And it is a negative
number. A negative number.
We can actually measure this tension with
a number of instruments. And I brought 1
of these instruments into the lecture today.
I hope some of you come up and look at it.
And this instrument measures tension in a
very unique way.
First of all let me describe the instrument
to you. It is called the Scholander
pressure chamber. And it consists of the following:
It consists of a heavily
thick-walled pressure chamber, like so, which
is connected to a meter. And this meter is
then connected to a gas, a cylinder of compressed
gas. This is the Scholander pressure
bomb used for measuring tension.
Now how does this work? Here's a plant which
I cut yesterday. And during the time,
although it's been in water, if I had taken
it out of water and let it sit in the lab,
this plant would have been transpiring. The
water molecules in this particular plant
would be in a condition of high tension. So
here we have a stem which has been
transpiring all night. And here are the water
molecules, and they're really stretched
between each other because they're under high
tension. High tension.
How do we measure that tension? If I take
these cutters here and I cut the stem like
so, so we have now these two parts of the
stem, what does this do to the water column?
So
here is the stem now which has been cut. And
now what we've done is we've severed the
water column and we've released the tension.
So the water molecules now pull back from
the cut surface with very little space
between the individual water molecules. Tension
has been released.
Now, so that's these two parts over here now.
Now how does the pressure bomb work? The pressure
bomb works by taking in this
particular case this top shoot system and
putting it into the top of the chamber which
is
over here like so. So I put the, with the
end of the stem sticking out. And it's, this
is usually tightened down. I increase the
gas pressure. And now what I'm going to ask
is
how much pressure do I have to put on this
plant here to push the water back to the point
that it was at before I cut the stem?
We read that number off of this dial here.
And that gives us a measure of how much
positive pressure we have to put in to restore
the water column back to the point that it
was prior to the time that I cut it. That
number is a positive number. And now because
the plant is under tension, in order for us
to get a reading as to what is going on, we
have to now give you a negative number in
order for the tension to be given a real value.
So tension is indicated by a negative number.
Anybody have any questions? This is an important
concept. Tension or psi sub-p is
a negative number. Yes.
STUDENT: [inaudible]
PROFESSOR: The Scholander pressure chamber
is set up exactly as we have it here,
except there's a small tank of pressurized
gas which I didn't bring in. And the great
part about this pressurized chamber is it's
portable. People who are physiologic
ecologists can take this into the field with
them and can actually do measurements of
plants in their actual site. You can tell
how much tension a plant is under because
these
chambers are portable.
Any other questions? Okay.
Now, having talked to you a little bit about
water relations and at least these three
components -- psi sub-pi, psi sub-p, and psi
-- which affect water movement, what I'd
like to do is to move on now to talking to
you about some real situations with regard
to
water molecules and with regard to water movement.
And the situation which I'd like to discuss
with you is one that we have allude to
for much of the class. Namely, what I'd like
to discuss with you is the control of pore
size in stomata via changes. So water is distributed
throughout the plant. And it's
destruction does many things. It carries along
with it nutrients. It removes nutrients
from photosynthate to take them to storage
organs. But water is also used in many other
processes.
And I'd like to discuss with you some of the
other processes that water is used in.
And the one I'd like to begin with is the
guard cell or stomata situation of which we
have
talked about already quite a lot.
So let's begin by drawing for you a typical
stomatal setup, which as we said consists
of a pore and two guard cells. And what we
said over here is that the size of the pore
is
important in determining whether or not CO2
can enter and water can leave. And what we
want to explore now is the fact that the size
of the pore is controlled by water or more
abstractly by water potential.
Now in order to appreciate how this works,
so in some circumstances the pore is open.
And now in the other circumstance which we
have also illustrated before and I'll show
you
some slides of this in a moment, in this other
circumstance, the pore can be closed, a
closed pore. And we have the guard cells again
surrounding this closed pore.
How do we go from these two particular states
and how is this related to water? In
order for you to appreciate this I'm going
to show you some slide of it because it's
a
hard concept to do. You have to know two facts.
The first fact is that the guard cells, which
I'll just abbreviate as GC, are
tightly attached to each other
at their ends. And the second fact which is,
of course,
something we have referred to a number of
times in talking about different cell types
is
that the guard cells are alive. That is they
have a membrane. So each of these cells has
a membrane surrounding it.
So let's now follow the steps in moving from
a closed pore as illustrated above to an
open pore. What goes on?
So in going from closed to open, how does
this happen? Well let me tell you what the
endpoint is in order for this to happen and
then we'll say how we got there. The endpoint
is that pressure has to increase in the guard
cell.
How does this pressure increase? Number one,
solutes moved into the guard cells. So
across that membrane we now move solutes.
Number two, the water potential of the guard
cells becomes more negative. And number three,
water enters the guard cell causing an
increase in pressure and opening of the pore.
Let's look at this increase in pressure inside
the guard cell as a result of water
coming in. So here's our pore. Here is one
of the guard cells with its membrane. And
now the pore is open because water has come
in and increased the pressure. So water has
moved in to the guard cells. Water in. And
as a result, pressure inside rises.
So water is coming in, and now pressure inside
the guard cells is increasing. And
that pressure is pushing out on the walls
of the guard cell as more water comes in.
Think of it as a balloon. As you're blowing
more air into the balloon, the balloon
is inflating more. Think of the wall of the
balloon as the cell wall or the membrane.
And think of the air as water.
This pressure inside is a positive pressure.
And we call this positive pressure
turgor pressure. And we can measure it. And
it is illustrated by the sign psi sub-p
again.
So in turgor pressure, psi sub-p is positive
in turgor pressure. But in tension,
psi sub-p is negative. So this symbol psi
sub-p can be either positive or negative,
depending upon whether you are in a cell that's
alive with a membrane or a cell that is
dead as the xylem element is.
Let's look now at a few pictures of the stomatal
system we've talked about. Okay the
first slide is meant to illustrate for you
what you have seen before. Namely, that we
have the epidermis of the leaf where transpiration
is occurring. We have the pore, and on
either side of the pore are the two guard
cells. And I want to again call your
attention -- and we'll look at this more closely
in a cartoon -- to the fact that the
guard cells are tightly joined to each other
at their ends. And that when pressure
increases, this causes the two cells to push
apart from each other, to bow out. And this
accounts for the opening of the pore.
You can see this joining of the end walls
in this scanning electromicroscope picture
of the guard cells where they are attached.
They are very expanded, again because of
turgor pressure inside. And this turgor pressure
exists because of the membrane which now
allows for solutes to accumulate and for an
increase in water pressure inside.
Here we have now the movement of water in
following a movement of solutes. And the
water moving in causes the two cells to bow
out from each other and the pore to open.
When the guard cell closes, we move the solutes
out of the guard cell. And when the
solutes go out, the water potential of the
guard cells becomes more positive relative
to
the cells outside. And, it becomes more positive,
and the water then leaves or the cells
close.
So in this particular case we have a very
nice system which depends upon a simple
change in water potential.
Now what is the solute that moves in and out
between these two cells? We now know
that the main solute that the cells move across
is potassium. Potassium is the element
which changes the water potential which the
plant selectively moves across the guard cell
membrane in order to allow the guard cells
to open or close.
Now just to use maybe something too much,
here's a cartoon of two balloons meant to
illustrate for you the two guard cells. And
what we've done is to attach the two ballons
at their end. And then to ask your graduate
student to blow-up the balloon as if the air
was going in was water. And when you blow-up
the balloons, when they're attached at their
ends, you create this space in between. And
this is the mechanism by which the guard
cells open.
Now finally, what I want to do is to talk
to you a little bit more about turgor
pressure. The form of plants, the fact that
when a plant is growing well in your yard
and
you've watered it, the form of a plant is
due to the fact that a plant has high turgor
pressure. When a plant wilts, when it collapses,
it is because you have removed the
turgor pressure to a point that it is no longer
pressing against the cells and thereby,
the plant's form changes.
And so what I'd like to do is to illustrate
for you a small experiment to look a
little more closely at turgor pressure and
to look at one aspect of the turgor pressure
that you're going to see in the lab.
And that aspect is the following: We're going
to take a cell which is fully turgid.
Fully turgid. That is turgor pressure, turgor
pressure is pushing out. Turgor pressure
is pushing out.
Now what we're going to do is to take this
cell which is full turgor pressure, and
let's just say for our experiment that we
have here that the water potential, let's
just
say the water potential of the cell is -4,
just for our discussion. It's got some salts
inside. It's got a lot of water inside.
And now what we want to do is take this cell
which now has a psi equal to -4, and
we're going to put it inside of a beaker in
which we, or series of beakers, where we
change the size. And we make them more negative.
So we may have -5, -6, -7. You're actually
going to do this experiment in the lab.
And what's happening to this cell if it is
put into a solution which has a water
potential more negative than it? Well, water
is more pure inside the cell. It has a
higher water potential even though it's a
negative number. So water's going to leave
the
cell. Everybody clear on that? It's going
to leave the cell, following the gradient
in
psi from where it is more pure to where it
is less pure.
So what we're going to see happening as we
increase the water potential inside the
beaker is soon we begin to lose, we have a
loss of psi sub-p or turgor pressure, at
which point the cell begins to shrink. It
actually is inflated as a result of the turgor
pressure. And the cell begins to now contract
as we're withdrawing water from it.
During this initial contraction, the membrane,
this is the membrane now, is still
against
the wall. But eventually as we withdraw more
water from the cell, that is put it
in increasingly more negative solutions on
the outside, we reach the point where the
cell
cannot contract anymore. It's now totally
relaxed.
However, we're still withdrawing water from
that cell. At that point what we notice
is that the membrane is beginning to pull
away from the cell wall. So at some point
the
membrane pulls away. And we call that point
which you're going to measure in the lab,
we
call that point incipient plasmolysis. And
the reason why it's so important to be able
to
measure incipient plasmolysis is at incipient
plasmolysis, psi sub-p for that particular
cell equals zero. So this is why we want to
be able to measure by putting it in
increasingly more salty or solute-bound solutions
when the membrane pulls way, because
when it pulls away, we know that the psi sub-p
of that cell and you need to know this
fact for the problems that we give you, the
psi sub-p of the cell equals 0.
Let's now look at a few pictures of plasmolysis.
And I also want to mention to you
that I have a couple of YouTube links listed
on the syllabus which show plasmolysis. And
I'd encourage you all to look at those links
before you come to the lab and do the
experiment so you know what you're looking
at.
Here is a cell which is now put into solution
with a water potential equal to its
own. The membrane is directly against the
cell wall. And as we begin to withdraw water,
the membrane is pulling away from the cell
wall, which is what you see over here, until
we've withdrawn so much water, that is the
water potential outside is so much more
negative that the cell has begun to collapse.
So this would be considered perhaps just a
little bit beyond incipient plasmolysis
but fairly close to it.
Here is some pictures of cells now that you're
going to have in the lab. The reason
they're purple, we choose cells that are purple
because we need to have some marker that
you can see. These cells have an anthocyanin
pigment in them which give them the purple
color.
And you're going to do this with onions. Here
with the onion cells that are fully
turgid. And as we put them in increasingly
more salty solutions, that is solutions of
increasingly more negative water potential,
we cause the membranes to pull away from the
cell wall until we have a completely plasmolyzed
cell.
And finally I just want to point out to you
what I mentioned earlier. Namely, that
the wilting of a plant, the loss of the form
is a result of the loss of turgid pressure.
Okay, make sure you spend some time on that
problem set. It will really help you
with these concepts.