PROFESSOR: How's that? Is that better? Okay,
good. Are we
good?
So just about statements and protests. Before
ten past the hour,
that's fine. Our chancellor has a policy about
encouraging free speech. And so
that will be the policy that we have. But
after ten past, then it's for the
class. All right, here we are. Second lecture
in the ecology section. Great
to see you here. I know you've got something
else on your mind, like, exam on
Wednesday evening. I do want to point out
that Professor Shabble has two
reviews. Today, 12:00 to 1:30 and also Wednesday,
12:00 to 1:30, room 2195,
which is one of the labs down the hall. I'll
have office hours. I don't expect
you there this week. Next week perhaps. Those
are in 5045 VLSB.
Last time we talked about, sort of, patterns
of solar radiation.
We talked about where the winds come from
on earth. We talked about how the
winds strive. The ocean currents. And the
winds and ocean currents and how
they move around the earth, set up a series
of predictions. If organisms are
distributed around the earth because of dispersal,
we predict that they're
either being blown by the winds or being moved
by the ocean currents and if
that's the case, we expect these organisms
and their ecology and their life
histories and their phylogenies to reflect
those patterns of wind movement and
ocean currents.
Today we're going to talk about a different
hypothesis. And that
is, we know that continents were, at various
times connected and disconnected.
We have a very good geological history now,
for the movement of the continents
and this sets up another set of hypotheses
and another set of predictions. We
know the history of the continents, we know
how they separated and came
together. For those organisms that don't disburse
much and just stay put, we
would expect those organisms and their phylogenies
to match those of the
continents. So that's what we're going to
talk about today.
First, we're going to discuss biomes, these,
sort of, sets of
organisms on earth that resembled each other
in different parts of the earth.
We'll talk about geological history. And then
we'll also talk about how human
activities have influenced the distribution
of organisms.
I just want to back up -- oops, sorry about
that -- just to
review one thing from last time. So the sun
hits the earth. It is hottest at
the equator. In fact, the book suggests the
statistic that where the sun is
actually hitting the upper atmosphere, it's
equivalent to 1,400 watt lightbulbs
in a cubic meter. So if you think of a cubic
meter and 1,400 watt lightbulbs,
those are pretty bright, that's a lot of solar
radiation hitting the earth. And
it is hottest at the equator. At the equator
it heats up the air, shown there
[Indicating] -- I'll try this again. Here
we go.
Heats up the air here [Indicating] Especially
at the equator.
That hot air can absorb a lot of moisture.
It also rises because it's warm.
And the air gets into the upper atmosphere,
it starts to cool down, and then it
releases that moisture. And that's why the
tropics are so wet of the air has to
go somewhere. Some goes North and some goes
South. It's dry air. And when it
comes back to earth, that dry air is coming
roughly, at 30 degrees North and
30 degrees South latitude. It is dry air and
so when it comes to earth, those
places on earth tend to be where we have the
deserts at 30 degrees North and
South.
And it was as I mentioned, because of the
rotation of the earth
and what's called the Coriolis Effect, the
winds are moved, either towards the
east or the west depending on whether they're
going North or South and which
latitude -- which hemisphere you're in.
And those winds are also driving the ocean
currents and as I just
mentioned, the winds and the ocean currents
make predictions if animals disburse
and that way as to how they should be distributed
on earth. All right, that's a
quick review from last time. Any questions
about that? I had a couple of
questions after class.
We talked a little bit about Mediterranean
climates last time.
We, of course, are in a Mediterranean client
here in the Bay Area. We talked
also, about these graphs called climate graphs,
climographs, climate diagrams.
There are different words for them. Shown
here. Here is San Francisco. We get
a lot of rain usually in the winter time.
Not much in the summer. Our
temperature is a little bit hotter in the
summer than it is in the winter time
of the there are other places on earth that
have similar patterns of climate.
Portugal is one of these. Of course, Portugal
is actually in the
Mediterranean region, a climate pattern very
similar to ours, a little bit
hotter in the summer time. Another place -- so
here is France, for example,
which is pretty no matter Portugal, and like
us, we're just a little below
40 degrees North latitude. The mediterranean
region is about the same. And you
can see some similarities here between these
kinds of habitats. They're both
kind of scrubby habitats, chaparral sorts
of habitats.
Even though the plants are different, they've
converged to a
similar kinds of communities and similar kinds
of adaptations. And we'll see
more of that when we go to the botanical garden
later in the semester. Okay.
And southern hemisphere, however, the pattern
is reversed, and
I'm sure you can figure out why that's the
case. In the southern hemisphere
they get most of their rain in the mediterranean
climates in the middle of the
year, which, of course, is their winter. It's
hotter in January -- December,
January, in the southern latitudes which,
of course, is their summer.
So I'm using this just as an example to point
out that we have
different regions of the earth that share
vegetation characteristics and those
plants and animals in those habitats also
share characteristics. And this is a
great example of mediterranean climates in
the northern hemisphere, but also in
the southern hemisphere and in is South America,
Africa and parts of Australia.
Okay. So these general relationships and patterns
and
similarities of habitats across the earth
attracted the attention of early
naturalists. Von Humboldt, in the last two
centuries ago, in the late 1800s,
noticed this. And this is one of his illustrations
from a mountain top in
Ecuador.
He noticed that as you go up the mountain,
you get different
kinds of vegetation from the bottom to the
top. And very recently, actually,
some researchers from Berkeley retraced his
steps and documented whether these
organisms were moving up and down the mountain.
We'll come back to that later
in the class.
So he had this idea that, with elevation and
also with latitude
your you get different kinds of ecological
communities. And now we recognize
this as a major pattern in ecology, and we
call these biomes. Biome is a
characteristic habitat, in terrestrial habitats
they're defined as both
latitude, but also vegetation characteristics.
And we see different biomes as
we go up in elevation. It gets colder, the
temperature and precipitation are
different. And we also see different biomes
as we move from the equator North
and South on earth.
We'll be discussing in this, in the ecology
section, quite a bit.
We'll be discussing these two features of
weather and climate, that is
temperature and precipitation. And we'll see
in future lectures, how
temperature and precipitation are very important
for primary productivity which
is where all the energy comes from to support
life on earth.
Here is a plot of mean annual precipitation
and mean annual
temperature. And it was a best of your knowledge
of different, of these
so-called biomes are plotted here. So we have
on the top right here, we have
tropical forests shown in dark green. With
a little bit less, a little colder
temperature, temperate deciduous forest shown
there in brown. As it gets less
precipitation and a little bit hotter, Savanna
is shown there. And Taiga here,
which is a wet carnivorous forest of the northern
latitudes, shown here where
it's a lot cooler. Just about near zero. And
still some precipitation.
So we can classify all these biomes based
on precipitation and
temperature. And I frequently get the question:
Well, do I have to memorize
all those biomes? The answer is no, but if
I were to give you a graph like
this, that's unlabeled and I said: Okay, point
out the desert or point out the
tropical rain forests. You should be able
to do that based on temperature and
precipitation. Make sense? Okay.
If we look at these terrestrial biomes around
the earth, here we
see them. I've just noted on there where the
equator is running through the
middle of the earth, 30 degrees North and
30 degrees South which we've talked
about the before. Here is 30 degrees North.
[Indicating] And you can see that
in this area we get some of the desert biomes
here and Savanna, these lighter
colors. [Indicating] Towards the equator we
have a band of tropical forest
biomes. And then I think it's quite -- oops,
sorry.
I think it's interesting to look at where
we live ourselves in
this region. We're just South of a region
of temperate evergreen forest. If
you've ever been to Vancouver or Seattle,
Washington, you know that some of
those forests there can be very lush and green.
And certainly The Redwoods
would be that kind of a forest. And you'll
see a great example of those in the
botanical gardens. We also have in this habitat
around us, Chaparral, which is
this dry, scrubby biome that's very characteristic.
If you walk into Strawberry
Canyon and you look about, or if you're from
the Bay Area, or, actually, most of
California, you'll know what that is.
Okay. The book -- your book mentions eight
major biomes and then
six other ones. I've just put a box here and
I've given you a list at the end
of the ones you should probably know something
about. Again, I don't expect you
to know every place on earth where each of
these biomes is found, but if I were
to say: What's characteristic of a tropical
rain forest or, you know, how is
Taiga different from the Tundra. You should
know those kinds of things.
And in a second I'm going to show you a bunch
of videos that
describe these because you're probably not
into each of these. All right, so
let me turn this down.
So here is a video that shows tropical rain
forests. And one
thing to remember about this is you'll see
just a vast amount of biome mass in
tropical rain forests that's actually in wood.
So the Carbon in tropical rain
forests is stored in the wood, in the trees.
And that's very different from
some of these other biomes, like the Savanna,
which I'll talk about in a minute,
where a lot of the biome mass is actually
stored in the bodies of these big
mammalian herbivores examine no the in the
cellulose in the plants.
All right.
VIDEO: In this South America rain forest the
day length and
temperature change little. Only an annual
cycle of rain and dry marks the
seasons. With such stable conditions and relentless
productive, organisms can
become specialists in an infinite variety
of narrow niches. (Howling.)
The result is an explosive speciation and
a staggering diversity
of plants and animals. In six percent of the
earth's surface, are half of the
planet's species. A patch of rain forests
can contain more species of trees
than the entire Northeastern United States.
[Music]
Biologists estimate there are between five
and 30,000,000 species
of animals in rain forests. They can't count
them more accurately than that.
And the number is probably changing as we
watch. If one species appeared on
this screen, every second, it would take nearly
a year to see 30,000,000.
[Music]
But the stability of the rain forest is challenged.
This is an
expanding network of roads in the Amazon Valley.
The image was compiled from
satellite photographs taken over several years.
In this photograph, taken from
the space shuttle, the light colored area
are fields from which the forest has
been completely cleared. What will be the
result of such wholesale disruption
of the rain forest?
PROFESSOR: Okay. So that thought we'll come
back to that, and
we'll talk about how habitats have changed.
By the way, I'll put all these
videos on the bCourses website in a folder
for you as well. Thanks for the
lights.
Next we're going to talked about the Savanna
and in contrast to
the rain forest where I have just huge amounts
of Carbon stored in all those
trees, and, of course, the trees of the forest
are pulling in Carbon from the
atmosphere. In the Savanna, we have a habitat
where the primary productivity is
grass. That's much more ephemeral in nature.
[VIDEO]
VIDEO: -- the forest, the constant supply
of water allows
primary producers to dominate. On the plains
of east Africa where the seasonal
rains make the water supply unreliable, grasses
replace trees as the primary
producers. Here there is a shift of biomass
to the large and abundant animal
life. Why can grasses survive here where trees
cannot? Trees invest most of
their biomass in woody structures aboveground,
that must be sustained in all
weather conditions. Most of the biomass of
these perennial grasses is below
ground. And the aboveground shoots are expendable
in dry periods. The shoots
grow when it rains.
The expendable shoots are also such an abundant
and accessible
food source, that the size and number of grazers
is breathtaking. In the
grasslands of Africa, a large part of the
biomass is in the animals, not the
plants. (Mosquitoes Buzzing).
The volcano soil is rich and full of nutrients.
The grasses make
the nutrients available to the herbivores
who reproduce to the limits of what is
available and a bit beyond. The apparent abundance
of food means nothing to a
single individual, only that there are more
individuals to compete with, for it.
PROFESSOR: Okay, so that's another could have
biome. Again, for
these biomes, what I expect you to know is
just the general characteristics of
each of those that I've listed at the end
of the lecture. And especially how
the different biomes contrast with each other.
And be able to roughly draw them
on that figure that shows precipitation and
temperature. We can talk more about
that later in the semester.
Okay, aquatic biomes, we're typically less
familiar with. We
don't have, you know, identifiable names,
usually, for aquatic biomes.
The aquatic biomes, of course, around the
earth. We know a lot
about the ocean zones, enter tidal zones,
coral reefs. And then those are the
marine, sort of, aquatic zones. And then we
have fresh water zones as well,
which is a small proportion of all water on
earth. And those are represented in
lakes and rivers. And, again, I've asked you
to learn a few of these. Sorry.
They're shown here.
[Indicating]
Intertidal zones, estuaries, coral reefs,
rivers and lakes. And
within each of these aquatic biomes we have
different kinds of habitats, and
these habitats and aquatic systems are defined
by physical characteristics,
unlike the terrestrial biomes which were defined
by vegetation characteristics
and latitude. So I'm just going to draw a
couple of these over here. These are
some figures from your book. Let's see here.
So this is, sort of, a cross-section. And
I'm going to talk
about a lake first. Here is the ground in
the lake. And here is the water
surface. So this is a lake. And right here
where the -- here is some -- sorry.
Here is some trees.
And then there's typically some vegetation
by the shore. Can you
see that? If not, you can look on the video
later. Right here, where the water
meets the shore, we call that -- sorry this
is hard to see -- the littoral zone.
And then this is the lake, the lake bottom.
And there's a part
of the lake where the light actually comes
down into the water. We call that
the photic zone, and then below that, aphotic.
Photic, meaning light, and
aphotic, below. And those are the components
of a lake ecosystem. And the
biomes, if you will, associated with lakes.
All right, and it was in marine systems we
have something that's
very, very similar. So we have the land. Sometimes
we have a continental shelf
and then it goes way down into the deeper
ocean. Here is our water and the sun
again and some trees.
Okay, where the ocean meets the land, of course,
that's the
intertidal zone. Then we also note on a layer
of the ocean that's above the
continental shelf, we call that the neritic
zone. Actually, I'll write that
down.
Neritic, n-e-r-e-t-i-c. And these words are
all at the end of
the lecture for you. And then as we had for
the lakes, we have a photic zone.
And below that aphotic. The surface at the
bottom, we call benthic. And lake
biologists also call the surface benthic.
Let's see.
Benthic. And then just on two more. The open
ocean we think of
as pelagic So the open ocean here is pelagic.
And then I won't write it, but
there are parts of the ocean that are really,
really deep and we call those the
abyssal zone. I'll show you that in a minute.
Okay, so just to summarize, lots of water
on earth. We'll come
back to the meaning of that and productivity
in other lectures. Most of it is
marine which means salty, and we can't drink
that. The fresh water is a small
portion of all of water on earth, maybe 20
percent arrow so, in lakes and
rivers. And these are distributed around the
earth. So just like the
terrestrial biomes, I'm going to show you
a few videos of some of the marine
biomes here.
So on the lower left here is one of these
hydrothermal vents deep
it in the ocean. It's a place where the continental
plates are spreading apart
and there's typically volcanic activity. Hydrogen
Sulfide, which some marine
organisms can use and actually oxidize creating
the basis for a whole ecosystem
down there. Here are a few pictures showing
what it's like down there.
Some worms here that are attached to the surface.
And then coral
reef habitats.
[VIDEO]
SPEAKER: Over the oceans of the world war,
only shallow tropical
waters offer the warm temperatures and reliable
productivity needed to maintain
a coral reef ecosystem. The coral polyps and
other invertebrates filter
plankton and harbor photosynthetic microorganisms
to bring energy into the
reef's food chain. In turn, other invertebrates
and fish graze on the filter
feeders.
Here, the plant and animal diversity is immense.
A reef may
contain as many as 100 species of coral, countless
other invertebrates and
several hundred species of fish. This large
nudibranch is a gas tetrapod
mollusk that probably grazes on sponges. It
lays thousands of eggs had this
fragile rosette.
Nudibranchs come in many shapes, sizes and
colors. They are
often highly specialized feeders. This is
a tunicate, a near relative of the
vertebrates. They are filter feeders. They
pump water in one opening and on
you the other extracting food particles and
oxygen. This large yellow sponge is
also a filter feeder.
PROFESSOR: Okay, So these are some rain habitats.
I gave you a
link to a really cool video of an Angler Fish
that was taken by a submersible
craft by the Monterey bay MBARI. I'm not sure
what that stands for, but it's a
research institute that's located on Monterey
Bay and associated with the
Hopkins -- with the Monterey Bay Aquarium.
Okay, just as we saw for, when we were talking
about climate and
weather, we had global patterns of precipitation.
There are also some local
phenomena important in aquatic ecosystems.
And one of these has to do with
seasonal turn over in temperate lakes.
As, you know, when lakes freeze over, because
of the unusual
characteristics of water, the lake can actually
be colder. The ice forms at the
top which is zero degrees, and that can actually
be colder than the bottom of
the lake which can be three or four degrees
because water happens to be most
dense at three or four degrees centigrade.
So in the winter time in temporal
areas, we typically have colder water at the
top and warmer water at the bottom.
In the summer time the reverse is true. The
sun heats up the
tops of the lakes and the top of the lake
is warmer than the bottom. And you
know this if you have been swimming in lakes.
Often, you can swim at the top of
the lake and you put your feet down or you
dive down a little bit and it gets
quite cold.
So this is an important characteristic of
water. It means that
when organisms are in lakes, in the winter
time, they don't necessarily freeze
all wait to the bottom. In fact, life can
persist in the bottom of lakes even
when the lakes are frozen over. This idea
of seasonal turn over is an important
one. Again, it just happens this temperate
regions where there's a big
difference it temperature between summer and
winter. So on the idea is that, in
the winter time, this photo on the left, there
could be ice at the top. But you
can see the temperature at the top is zero
degrees where the ice is. And it was
actually is warmer as you go down because
the densest -- water is most dense at
four degrees.
In the mid summer, we have the opposite. We
have hotter water at
the top. Colder water at the bottom. And then
what happens both in the spring
and fall is that the temperature relationship
in the lake turns over completely.
And this is called overturn or turnover. And
the idea is that, at some point in
the fall and some point in the spring, the
whole lake gets mixed up as the
temperature resorts itself.
And this gradient in temperature is called
a thermal climb, which
you can have in the winter and in the is summer.
And this is one thing that
keeps temperate lakes, especially, productive
in that the nutrients get sloshed
around at least twice a year. Also, it means
that if a lake does use up all of
its Oxygen in the summer time, when this turnover
happens in the fall and again
in the spring it can mix up the water and
provide Oxygen again.
These photos -- actually, I grew up in Maine
and these photos are
from very close to where I lived. Okay, next
we're going to move onto
continental drifts. So what we've seen so
far today is biomes, both in
terrestrial systems and aquatic systems. In
terrestrial systems, the biomes are
defined by vegetation and latitude. In the
aquatic systems the biomes are
defined by the physical characteristics. And
we talked about those, whether
it's, you know, light or the kind of habitat
that we saw for both marine and
fresh water systems.
All right, so, again, I have a video here
to show you continental
drift. But the idea is that, like we had when
we understood the disbursal of
organisms, based on wind currents or water
currents, we can also induce some of
the distribution of life on earth if we know
something about the continents,
where those organisms are living. And if the
organisms are not disbursing too
much and if they evolve before the continents
split apart, then we should expect
that their current distribution reflects that
of the history of the continents.
[VIDEO]
SPEAKER: The continents lie on massive plates
that are in
constant motion on earth's surface. Their
movement produces continental drift.
Sometimes forcing continents together and
another times pull them apart. Around
500 million years ago, earth's continents
were mostly in the southern hemisphere
and continued to move southward. Around this
time, the continents began to
coalesce into larger land masses. The largest,
Gondwana, included the future
South America, Africa, India, Australia, and
Antarctica. Around 400 million
years ago the large southern and northern
land masses began to approach each
other. In the Permian period, they collided
and formed a super continent called
Pangea.
The trigger caused volcanic eruptions. Lava
flowed and airborne
ash blocked sunlight. Cooling the climate
and triggering glaciation. By
150 million years ago, the northern continents
were completely separated from
the southern ones. As the continents continued
to move, India and Australia
drifted northward to their positions in present
day earth. When India collided
with Asia, the Himalayan mountain range was
formed.
PROFESSOR: Okay. So you're probably asking:
What do I have to
remember from that? Really, all I want you
to know is -- geologists know a lot
about the history of the earth and this history
is really well-known. We also
have very precise estimates for when all this
happened. And so we can use these
estimates to help us understand the diversity
of life on earth, but I don't
expect you to know really all of that, that
we just saw. Except maybe that
there are some southern continents that were
once together and are now apart.
One thing I thought was pretty cool and maybe
you didn't miss it
or maybe you missed it, but we'll come back
to it is that New Zealand and
Australia were actually two of the first parts
of this big southern continent to
break apart even though they're quite similar.
And we in the northern
hemisphere kind of think of them as all the
same place. But actually New
Zealand and Australia were some of the first
land masses to split from this
southern continent. That will become important
in just a second.
Okay, as I said, geologists have a really
good feeling for this.
It's remarkable that all of what we know about
continental drift is really only
50, 60, 70 years old, but it has really revolutionized
what we think about life
on earth. And here, just some of the plates.
You know, a lot about the Pacific
plate and the North American plate because
they're sliding by each other. Here
in California which creates our earthquakes.
Some of these plates, you'll notice, are splitting
apart creating
these big ridges in the middle of the ocean.
Some are coming together. For
example, the Indian plate smashing into the
Eurasian plate creating the
Himalayan mountains and so on. So we have
those actions that are splitting
continents apart and we also have actions
that are pushing these continents
together.
As a result of this movement of the plates,
those organisms that
evolved in those places are being split apart
from each other and in some cases,
they're coming back together. So let me just
show you.
So let's just look at a few of these. So this
figure is kind of
cool in that it shows the years since these
different parts of the earth were
joined together. So, for example -- just a
second here.
South America and Africa were last joined
about 100 million years
ago. The tip of Antarctica I can from Australia,
also 100 million years ago.
New Zealand and Antarctic, 80 million, but
parts of Australia and South America
to Antarctica, you know, only 40 or 50 million
years ago. You don't have to
remember those numbers. I just want you to
get the idea that geologists know a
lot about this. And it makes this set of predictions
that we're going to use in
a minute.
There are also places where the plates are
coming together. For
example, South America and North America smashed
together about 6 million years
ago and a lot of organisms went back and forth,
as you know already. When that
happens, we call that biotic exchange, where
organisms from different continents
meet, and exchange with each other because
they can. The same thing happened
here when the oriental plate hit the Palearctic
plate here, and then also with
Africa running into Europe.
All right, so the point there is that the
history these
continents makes for very clear predictions.
There are some places here, for
example, Wallace's Line here [Indicating]
There still are deep divisions between
parts of the earth that have been separated
for a very long time. And these can
be both marine and terrestrial systems. And
we'll come back to that in a
minute.
Well Wallace, as would you have heard about
in the evolution
section, thought a lot about life on earth,
and he divided the world up into
these biogeographic regions based on the kinds
of organisms that were there.
And this largely reflects the history of these
continents. And more recently --
and again this is just an example, but I don't
expect you to memorize it -- more
recently researchers have used phylogenetic
methods to look at the similarity of
organisms from these different places on earth.
And in this graph, the similar colors suggest
that or are used to
indicate similarity of different kinds of
organisms in these different places,
and colors that are very different from each
other are used to indicate
organisms that are very different phylogenetically
from each other.
And what you can see is that the Austral Australian
region there
has organisms that are very different from
the rest of the earth as are
Madagascar shown there in brown. North and
South America, they are different,
but there are some similarities. And then
a lot of similarities across Europe
and Asia and actually into Africa.
And these researchers also looked at more
detail at different
taxonomic groups and pretty much the same
pattern is shown in each of these
taxonomic groups. Australia is really different.
Amphibians at the top, of
course, they don't move over water very well.
And so you can see that places
like Madagascar, New Guinea there above Australia
and so on, are really
different. Birds here shown in the middle,
you can see that because birds fly
and they can move. They move between North
and South America. So there's some
similarity there. Oops, sorry about that.
Mammals also have moved across North and South
America, as you
know from understanding the history of things
like marsupials and raccoons and
things like that. Anyway, so this old idea
of Wallace's, that we have
biogeographic regions or zoographic regions,
we now know is largely based on the
continents moving around and the history of
these organisms tied to those
continents. And that's a process called vicariance
where the distribution of
organisms is the result of where they evolved.
Separations in these organisms in terms of
speciation or
diversification are due to geological processes.
And that's a very different
explanation for the distribution of life on
earth than dispersal, which is one
that says things are the way they are because
they've moved there regardless of
what the history of the continents were.
I want to come back for just some examples
of some of these
biogeographic barriers, and I want to point
out that these barriers concur both
in the marine systems as well as terrestrial
systems. There's an area between
Southeast Asia and Australia that has a very
dynamic geological history. And
over time, since the Pleistocene, with the
sea level going up and down, at
various times this area was connected and
became disconnected, which resulted
actually, and probably a lot of species being
formed as these land masses became
disconnected.
But there is a line in there where there is
deep water that was
never connected. And this is Wallace's Line,
which Wallace noted. And that
flows through here. There are also some other
deep trenches in the oceans. And
I want to just remind you, again, this abyssal
zone and we're going to take a
look at one of these deep ocean areas in this
video.
Okay, so this is James Cameron who is a noted
film maker. And
when you have just so much money and so much
time on your hands, what do you do?
You build a cool sub examining to the deepest
parts of the ocean. So let's see
this here.
[VIDEO]
NARRATOR: Pilot coming out. National Geographic
explore and
residence, James Cameron, has finished a record
dive to the deepest part of the
earth's ocean.
(Applause.)
MR. CAMRON: The Challenger Deep, which is
only a small part of
the Mariana Trench is something like 50 times
the size of the grand canyon of
the so, you know, this is a vast, you know,
frontier down there. It's going to
take us a while to understand.
NARRATOR: The dive follows seven years of
planning and the
design and construction of a specialized straight
of the art submersible for the
deepest solo man dive in history.
MR. CAMRON: The whole sub actually squeezes
down almost three
inches in length when it gets to the bottom
of the ocean just because of the
pressure. The sphere I'm in, actually shrinks
much the window that I look out
actually pushes in toward me under 16,000
pounds per square inch of pressure.
NARRATOR: Cameron spent more than three hours
in the lowest
point of the Mariana Trench about seven miles
down, filming and documenting what
he saw and taking samples.
MR. CAMRON: It was very lunar, very desolate
place, very
isolated. My feeling was one of complete isolation
from all of humanity. I
mean, I felt like I literally, in the space
of one day, had gone to another
planet and come back.
NARRATOR: Armed with an eat foot panel of
led lights and
cameras, Cameron will be able to share with
the rest of the world, a part of the
planet that is virtually unknown.
SPEAKER: Many of the animals that live there
have adapted to
this extreme pressure, this total darkness.
They're usually white. They have
no pigments. Some of them have eyes to see
bioluminescence. Some of them have
no eyes at all. It's completely alien world.
[Laughter]
NARRATOR: Cameron is the first person to reach
the deepest point
of the Mariana Trench in more than 50 years.
[Music]
PROFESSOR: Okay, there you go. In the time
that I have left I
have two things: First, I want to give you
an example of how we use that
information about vicariance to test predictions
about how organisms are where
they are. And this is sort of analogous to
what I did at the end of the last
lecture with the work of what Rosemary Gillespie
and I were doing looking at how
we can use predictions about dispersal, wind
and ocean currents to understand
why organisms are where they are.
So now, I want to give you two examples of
how researchers using
use information about continental drift to
test the same kinds of hypotheses,
but in this case, not dispersal, but vicariance
which I talked about.
And this is a textbook example of vicariance
and it refers to
this genius of plants, Nothofagus, called
the southern beech. And later in the
semester you'll go to the botanical garden
and you'll see these from both South
America and Australia and New Zealand shown
here.
So as we saw in the video, at one point this
Gondwana continent
was all connected and then it split apart.
And we can use those dates to test
whether the distribution of this beech lineage
is a result of that splitting
apart of the continents or whether we need
too explain their distribution with
some more recent dispersal. All right, and
the way this works is this.
We can make a cladogram that is a phylogeny
of the land masses,
and we call this an area cladogram. And that's
shown here. What this cladogram
shows is just really a tree, but it summarizes
when these different land masses,
New Zealand, New Caledonia, South America,
West Antarctica, New Guinea last
shared a connection. All right, so Australia,
New Guinea separated only ten to
15 million years ago.
Australia and this part of Gondwana separated
from New Zealand
and New Caledonia a long time ago, like, 80
to 90 million years ago. So that's
what this diagram shows. So then what we do
for any taxon, if we're interested
in weather, this explains the distribution.
We take that taxon, we make a
molecular phylogeny of the taxon itself and
we ask: Well, for any groups of
organisms in that phylogeny, how long ago
did they share on a common ancestor?
And then we can compare the real phylogeny
to that we know of the geology and
ask: Do they match or not? That is, is the
real phylogeny old enough to be
explained by this phylogeny of the land masses,
or do we need dispersal to
explain the new phylogeny?
All right, so people have done that. Sorry.
Here are the results. And this is just what
I just said in a
nutshell. That is, we get a molecular phylogeny
here on the right and we look
at different taxon in that lineage and we
say: When did they share a common
ancestor? And we can ask: Does that match
the phylogeny of the plates, the
geology?
So these gray bars here, the one on the left
there shows when
Australia and New Zealand were last connected,
that's 80 million years ago or
so. And the gray bar in the middle shows when
Antarctica, South America and
Australia were last connected, and that's,
like, 40 million years ago. And
shown in the top there are on a whole bunch
of these comparisons. Between at
the top there is South America and Australia,
and South America and Australia
for another taxon. And they use different
genes and look to see how different
these plants were, and they can put a date
on that based on this idea of
molecular clocks, with you know. And they
found at least for that set of taxon,
at the top, the observed dates from the biology
match the predictions from the
plate tectonics or continents moving very,
very well.
What we would say there is that: Yes, indeed
those plants are
where they are on earth because they've been
stuck on these continents that are
separated since that time.
However, there's another comparison here between
plants found in
New Zealand and Australia shown here on the
lower right. And what we see with
these observed dates for this group, is that,
in fact, these observed dates are
much too young to be explained by vicariance
in the continents moving. So the
dates between plants in Australia and New
Zealand are only, say, 20 million
years ago. We know that Australia and New
Zealand actually split up 80 million
years ago. So they must have disbursed from
one place to another much more
recently.
And this is not so unreasonable because we
know that Australia
and New Zealand are actually quite close to
each other. So maybe there's a
chance through either ocean currents or winds,
for these plants to move from one
of these places to the other. Okay, so that's
an example of how we can use
knowledge about the history of the continents
to say something about the history
of these organisms and the importance of disbursal.
And then just one slide before we go. Here
is another example.
And this was actually done by a student of
Rosemary Gillespie. This is an
Assassin Spider. This is really a spider.
Here is its jaws. So this is
actually its head and its eyes. This is its
body here, and these jaws are
really long, because it feeds on other spiders
and it wants to keep them at an
arm's length or at jaw's length so that the
other spider doesn't come and try to
kill this spider.
These spiders are also distributed around
the southern
continents, and I just want to leave you with
this point that, just like for the
last example -- and you don't need to read
this or understand this other than
the distribution of these organisms also,
is predicted by continental drift. So
sure, big trees and things like that that
might not disburse much. We might
expect them to follow these patterns, but
we also see that for animals that are
not highly dispersive.
Okay, that's it. We'll follow up with the
rest of this topic.
Again, there's a review session today from
12:00 to 1:30 and also Wednesday, and
your exam for the evolution section on Wednesday
evening.